# Youngwook Jung

in Y.W. Jung | ⊕ webpage | ✓ yj10@illinois.edu | ■ +1.217.377.1239

#### SUMMARY

I am a labor economist with research interests in labor and demographic economics. In my main research, I use causal inference methods to explore how the influx of prime-age workers affects marginal retirement-age workers in an area. I possess a strong interest in a diverse range of socioeconomic and industrial topics and enjoy collaborating in interdisciplinary environments.

## **EDUCATION**

2017–2024 (expected) Ph.D. Economics at University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC)

2015–2017 M.A. Economics at Sungkyunkwan University, Republic of Korea 2009–2015 B.A. Economics at Sungkyunkwan University, Republic of Korea

## RESEARCH FIELDS AND TOPICS

Labor and demographic economics; Regional labor markets, regional migration, firms, housing market

#### Working Papers

## ❖ Substitutability between prime-age and marginal retirement-age workers (Job Market Paper)

This study examines the substitutability between prime-age workers, aged 25–54, and marginal retirement-age workers, aged 55–64. It investigates the impact on the cohort of older workers when younger workers flow into an area and estimates the elasticity of substitution between the two cohorts. This research employs the use of instrumental variable and local projection techniques to establish robust causal inferences.

## ❖ Differential response of young and mature firms to labor demand shocks

The higher the share of workers in the construction industry, the more positive the impact on young enterprises. This is because in the construction sector, the marginal product of labor of young firms is higher than of mature firms. In a recession, young firms' employment is more reduced via asymmetric credit contraction.

## ❖ Determinants of adoption in value-added tax and changes in the tax rate

Fiscal contract theory suggests that taxes can increase with credible commitments between citizens and the government. However, this study finds that the theory is only partially applicable since political factors barely demonstrate the theory while some economic variables support it.

# RESEARCH IN PROGRESS

#### ❖ Higher house prices rob the poor's leisure time

Higher housing prices lead to increased commuting time via gentrification, particularly for low-skilled workers, and this in turn reduces their leisure time.

# ❖ Negative net migration and the local economy (with Geoffrey J.D. Hewings)

Income inequality in Illinois has declined due to a net outflow of highly educated workers, but the outflow of workers has additionally reduced output and income levels in the local economy through multiplier effects.

❖ Is this time really different? Impacts of COVID-19 on state and local economies and housing markets (with Jiyoung Chae, Ivan Caceres, and Geoffrey J.D. Hewings)

Focusing on the housing market in Illinois, the economic impacts of the period before and after the COVID-19 pandemic are compared to a comparable time during the Great Recession in 2008.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2019–2021 Research assistant to Prof. Geoffrey Hewings at Regional Economics Application Laboratory

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### Teaching Assistant

Fall 2022–Spring 2023 Macroeconomic Principles, Prof. Vazquez Jose

Spring 2022 Macroeconomic Principles, Prof. Ramses Armendariz Buaun

Fall 2016 Statistical Analysis for Economics, Prof. In-Moo Kim

Spring 2016 Mathematical Statistics (Graduate course), Prof. In-Moo Kim

#### FELLOWSHIPS AND AWARDS

| 2023        | Travel Award, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign                                     |
|-------------|--|
| 2017 – 2018 | Department Fellowship, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign                            |
| 2016        | The National Research Scholarship (Humanities and Social Sciences), funded by Korea Stu-     |
|             | dent Aid Foundation (2016-9012054987) for promising research projects in the social sciences |
| 2014 – 2015 | Cho Byeongdu Scholarship, granted by Cho, CEO of Dongju Co., for undergraduate students      |
|             | who demonstrate leadership and outstanding academic achievement                              |
| 2014        | Excellence Award, Undergraduate Paper Competition, hosted by Sungkyunkwan University         |
| 2013        | Excellence Award, International Development Competition, hosted by Korea Export-Import       |
|             | Bank   |
| 2013        | Special Award, Thesis Competition, hosted by Market Economic Research Institute              |
| 2012        | Best Prize, Thesis Competition, hosted by Korea Development Institute                        |
| 2010        | Best Research Paper, academic conference, hosted by Sungkyunkwan University                  |
|             |  |

#### SKILLS

Computational Stata, R (advanced), Python, SQL Languages English (fluent), Korean (native)

# ACTIVITIES AND COMMUNITIES

MENSA USA (Heart of Illinois Mensa)

Dasan Finance Club (served as a chief seminar organizer) in SKKU

Military Service (Sergeant, Republic of Korea Air Force)

# REFERENCES

Professor Greg Howard (Chair)

UIUC, Department of Economics

glhoward@illinois.edu

Professor Stephen L. Parente

UIUC, Department of Economics

parente@illinois.edu

Professor Geoffrey J.D. Hewings

UIUC, Institute of Government and Public Affairs

hewings@illinois.edu

Professor Alexander W. Bartik

UIUC, Department of Economics

abartik@illinois.edu

Last updated: April 30, 2023